Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף כ. Daf
Kaf. Also it's September 11th, so we should just
really thoughts with all of those who suffered losses and not only
the families and those who were in the building, but of course
the rescue workers who so many of them gave up their lives
and are even until today continuing to suffer illness related to those
events. So really our thoughts are with everybody who was impacted by
those horrific events 14 years ago. And also it's ראש השנה Rosh
Hashana is just around the corner and we're not doing a דף
daf on ערב ראש השנה Erev Rosh Hashana because of דאבנינג davening
issues. So just take the opportunity to wish everybody כתיבה וחתימה טובה
Ketiva Vchatima Tova and it should be a good תפילות Tefillot and
a powerful ראש השנה Rosh Hashana and and yeah, we will be
doing the דף daf on both days of ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana,
so check your schedules.
כתיבה וחתימה טובה Ketiva Vchatima Tova to everyone. Alright, we pick up
on the bottom of יט עמוד ב Yud Tet Amud Bet after
the משנה, Mishna, and the גמרא Gemara had the משנה Mishna had
just spoken about somebody who accepted a long נזירות Nezirut and then
they come to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So there's a sense of
an it very strategically or whatever significantly is juxtaposed to the משנה
Mishna of somebody accepting נזירות Nezirut in a בית הקברות Beit HaKevarot
where when you leave the בית הקברות Beit HaKevarot you start your
נזירות דטהרה. Nezirut de-Tahara. So here, obviously the status of חוץ לארץ
Chutz La'aretz as טמא Tamei is Rabbinic, and it would not be
a type and nobody's saying that really it סותר soter the נזירות,
Nezirut, but some level
there's a symbolic significance you come to Israel where you have to
come to bring your קרבנות Korbanot and now you're not in an
ארץ טמאה. Eretz Tmeia.
So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you do a symbolic 30-day additional
נזירות Nezirut and בית הלל Beit Hillel says no, now it's like
you're really בטהרה, be-tahara, now you have to do the whole thing
again. Not bringing a קרבן Korban obviously because you haven't ended your
first one yet, but now extend it. It's like you went from
טומאה tuma to טהרה tahara and now do the full length of
it and only at the end of that period bring a קרבן.
Korban. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. קתני רישא,
Ktani Reisha, it says in the beginning בית שמאי אומרים נזיר שלושים
יום בית הלל אומרים נזיר בתחילה. Beit Shammai Omrim Nazir Shloshim Yom
Beit Hillel Omrim Nazir Bat-chila. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you
do another 30 you do 30 days when you enter into ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael additional and בית הלל Beit Hillel says you extend
it you do the entire duration that you had of the נזירות.
Nezirut. So לימא בהא קמיפלגי, Lema Baha Kamipalgi, let's understand what this
debate is about. Why is it either doing 30 days or doing
the entire duration? בית שמאי סברי, Beit Shammai Savri, בית שמאי Beit
Shammai of the opinion ארץ העמים משום גושא גזרו עליה Eretz Amim
Mishum Gusha Gazru Aleha that ארץ העמים, Eretz Amim, the land of
the non-Jews חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, when they said it's טמא, Tamei,
what they treated as טמא Tamei was the גושא, gusha, the dirt.
ובית הלל סברי, Ve-Beit Hillel Savri, and בית הלל Beit Hillel of
the opinion משום אוירא גזרו עליה. Mishum Avira Gazru Aleha. It wasn't
just the dirt, it was even the very air. Now what that
means is let's say again for example somebody walks goes into ארץ
העמים Eretz Amim without touching the ground. He goes in a box
or he's being carried in some type of a thing and he
doesn't touch the ground. So if it's משום גושא Mishum Gusha you're
טהור, Tahor, if it's משום אוירא Mishum Avira you are טמא. Tamei.
Now, question about how is it different than טומאת אוהל? Tumat Ohel?
So first of all as we said non-Jews might not have טומאת
אוהל, Tumat Ohel, so it would only be if you actually touched
the ground. And second of all you can be in the air
without even avoiding טומאת אוהל Tumat Ohel problems. If you're let's say
in the air and you're suspended and there's something below you, so
if it were a real אוהל Ohel concern, it would hit the
bottom of it and spread and you would be safe if you
were in like being carried in a box or whatever above ground.
Anyway so that's the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית
שמאי. Beit Shammai. תוספות Tosafot also points out by the way that
it didn't have to say קתני רישא. Ktani Reisha. It's the גמרא
Gemara right after the משנה Mishna and it just starts to discuss
the משנה Mishna but once again pointing out that לשון נזיר Lashon
Nazir is שונה, shoneh, נדרים Nedarim is שונה shoneh right so it
says קתני רישא Ktani Reisha even though normally that's when you're already
in the middle of something and then you're referring back to the
beginning. Anyway so here's the debate of בית שמאי Beit Shammai and
בית הלל. Beit Hillel. So לימא בהא קמיפלגי, Lema Baha Kamipalgi, let's
understand what this debate is about. Why is it either doing 30
days or doing the entire duration? בית שמאי סברי, Beit Shammai Savri,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai of the opinion ארץ העמים משום גושא גזרו
עליה Eretz Amim Mishum Gusha Gazru Aleha
that ארץ העמים, Eretz Amim, the land of the non-Jews חוץ לארץ,
Chutz La'aretz, when they said it's טמא, Tamei, what they treated as
טמא Tamei was the גושא. gusha. ובית הלל סברי, Ve-Beit Hillel Savri,
and בית הלל Beit Hillel of the opinion משום אוירא גזרו עליה.
Mishum Avira Gazru Aleha.
It wasn't just the dirt, it was even the very air. Now
what that means is let's say again for example
somebody walks goes into ארץ העמים Eretz Amim without without a what
do you call it without touching the ground. He goes in a
box or he's being carried in some type of a thing and
he doesn't touch the ground. So if it's משום גושא Mishum Gusha
you're טהור, Tahor, if it's משום אוירא Mishum Avira you are טמא.
Tamei. No question about how is it different than טומאת אוהל? Tumat
Ohel? So first of all as we said non-Jews might not have
טומאת אוהל, Tumat Ohel, so it would only be if you actually
touched the ground. And second of all you can be in the
air without even avoiding טומאת אוהל Tumat Ohel problems. If you're let's
say in the air and you're suspended and there's something below you,
so if it were a real אוהל Ohel concern, it would hit
the bottom of it and spread and you would be safe if
you were in like being carried in a box or whatever above
ground. So but that's if it's משום גושא, Mishum Gusha, even if
there were an
אוהל Ohel concern, אוירא Avira is clearly much more serious, goes beyond
normal extent of
טומאת מת. Tumat Met. But what would it have to do with
this issue about whether you restart the whole נזירות Nezirut or not?
So the probably the... So the probably the easiest thing to say
here is is that if it's just a question about how weighty
you take it, if בית שמאי Beis Shammai just takes it like
גושה, gusha, now they gave it this status, but they didn't go
overboard. They treated the ground as טמא. tamei. Fine. So that's a
certain degree of weight. So therefore we'll just give you 30 days
because again it's all rabbinic anyway. בית הלל Beis Hillel thinks that
they gave it this enormous amount of weight that even the very
air is טמא. tamei. So that's going to be reflected, that weightiness
of how טמא tamei you're, you know, the land of חוץ לארץ
Chutz La'aretz is, is going to be reflected in how much we
demand that you now do when you leave that land, how much
we can give you any credit for the time you did when
you were in that land, given the weightiness that we have assigned
to that. Now תוספות, Tosafos, that's probably,
one minute,
let me just double check תוספות. Tosafos.
Yes, so if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos
doesn't like this. So תוספות Tosafos says:
לימא בהא קמיפלגי. Laima b'ha kamifligi. Let's just go to the fourth
line from the top, last of the wide lines. He says: ובית
הלל סברי אפילו על אוירא גזרו ומשום הכי החמירו לסתור הכל. U'Beis
Hillel savri afilu al avira gazru u'mishum hachi hichmiru lister hakol. Okay,
so that's what we said. That's just simple, weighty, it's weighty, it's
even the air. So if it's even the air, you can't get
any credit for the time you did in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz.
וקשה לגרסת זו. V'kashe legarsat zo. דמאי טעמא דבית שמאי? D'mai ta'ama
d'Beis Shammai? What's the logic of בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? דאינהו לא
גזרו כי אם משום גושה. De'inhu lo gazru ki im mishum gusha.
Even if they're more lenient and they only say it's the ground.
מכל מקום לסתור הכל. Mikal makom lister hakol. Once you're treating it
as טמא tamei and it's a concern of טומאת מת, tumas meis,
even if it's only rabbinic. Okay, so so what if it's still
only the ground and it's not overboard מחמיר? machmir? Still, be
consistent. מידי דהוה אבית הקברות דאינן מטמאי באויר. Midi d'havei abeis hakvaros
de'ainan mitamei be'avir. It's no different than normal טומאת מת. tumas meis.
Again, אויר avir means even avoiding אהל ohel issues. ואפילו הכי סותר
הכל. Va'afilo hachi soser hakol. וכן נראה דגרסינן איפכא. V'chein nireh d'garsinan
ipecha. And now תוספות Tosafos completely reverses the גירסא, girsah, which is
going to be a little counterintuitive. בית שמאי סברי משום אוירא גזרו.
Beis Shammai savri mishum avira gazru. בית שמאי Beis Shammai holds it's
the very air that's טמא. tamei. והחמירו בארץ עמים. V'hichmiru b'eretz ammim.
ובית הלל סברי משום גושה גזרו. U'Beis Hillel savri mishum gusha gazru.
And they're not so weighty. ואם תאמר. V'im tomar. לבית הלל נמי
מאי טעמא דבית שמאי? L'Beis Hillel nami mai ta'ama d'Beis Shammai? Okay,
I've reversed גירסא. girsah. How did I help anything? Now בית שמאי
Beis Shammai says it's weightier, the טומאה, tumah, and he's only going
to make you do 30 days. What's the logic? ויש לומר דאין
הכי
נמי. V'yesh lomar d'ein hachi nami. וכיון דהחמירו בה למיגזר על אוירא.
V'keivan d'hichmiru bei lister l'avira. If they're going so overboard that says
the very air is טמא. tamei. גלוי לכל דהאי טומאה אינה אלא
מדרבנן. Galui l'chol d'hai tumah einah ela miderabbanan. Clearly it's some made-up
טומאה דרבנן tumah derabbanan because no real טומאה tumah do you, are
you טמא tamei just by being in the air. Okay, just the
air makes you טמא. tamei. ולכך סגי ליה דיסתור שלשים יום דלא
מיחלפא בטומאה דאורייתא. U'l'kach sagi lei d'yister sheloshim yom d'lo michlifa b'tumah
de'oraisa. It doesn't get confused to be a real טומאה. tumah. בית
הלל סברי משום גושה גזרו. Beis Hillel savri mishum gusha gazru. No,
it's the ground. Like the ground is really טמא tamei because there
are buried bodies. וכיון דדמיא כקבר צריך שיסתור הכל. V'keivan d'dima k'kever
tzarich she'yister hakol. Okay, and because then people will really treat it
as real טומאת מת. tumas meis. So two interesting ways to say.
Is it that because if you go overboard of טומאת ארץ עמים
tumas eretz ammim and you're so weighty and you say that even
the air is טמא, tamei, you're going to also be really strict
and say you don't get any credit for the time you put
in in חוץ לארץ? Chutz La'aretz? That's one way of reading it.
Or תוספות Tosafos suggests the opposite. If you go so overboard, everybody
knows that this is some other rabbinic thing and they, and they,
you know, they don't treat it and it's not seen of in
the same category as a biblical טומאה. tumah. So there's no need
therefore to really make up the time in the same way. You
just do something symbolic. But if you treat it like you would
treat the דאורייתא de'oraisa טומאה, tumah, you only treat the ground as
טמא. tamei. So then you have to be, then you have to
be consistent. And if you're treating it in its normal parameters as
if it were a classic דאורייתא de'oraisa טומאה, tumah, then you're going
to now have to make up everything once you leave. So two
ways of reading the תוספות. Tosafos. You had your hand up from
before.
I was thinking about the air
issue. Airplanes that land in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael contain the air
of חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz.
Yeah, yeah, it's not when you, it's not when you export or
import the air. It's the air. Yes.
So when תוספות Tosafos says וכן נראה דגרסינן איפכא, v'chein nireh d'garsinan
ipecha,
he's changing the גירסא girsah of the text from a סברא. svarah.
Exactly. רש"י Rashi does it all the time. But תוספות Tosafos also
does it to some degree. I mean, it's also quite funny, you
know, because רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam for example, you know, in like
the beginning of ספר הישר Sefer Hayashar goes down and yells at
people who change גירסא. girsah. And
then, yeah, but then when they do it, exactly. Right. Yes. Okay,
all right. So that's that debate. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, לא, lo, so isn't that the debate? So back to the
גמרא. Gemara. לא דכולי עלמא משום גושה גזרו. Lo d'chulei alma mishum
gusha gazru. Everybody would say it's the dirt, and it's a normal
type of a טומאה, tumah, like as if it were טומאת מת,
tumat meis, although it's דרבנן. derabbanan. ובית שמאי סברי בסתם נזירות קנסינן
ובית הלל סברי כקנסינן בתחלת נזירות. U'Beis Shammai savri b'stam nezirus kansinan
u'Beis Hillel savri k'kensnan b'tchilas nezirus.
Which is not that helpful, right? No, everybody says it's a normal
טומאה, tumah, but בית שמאי Beis Shammai says we'll fine you, you
know, again because it was only rabbinic, so we'll fine you for
observing your נזירות nezirus in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz by doing one
symbolic נזירות, nezirus, and בית הלל Beis Hillel says no, we're going
to say as if you didn't do anything and you're going to
have to do it again from the beginning, which is not at
all helpful. Well that's just descriptive. It's not explanatory, right? We knew
that! Right, you've tried to explain it based on your attitudes of
how weighty the טומאה Tumah is in ארץ העמים. Eretz Ammim. They
said no, no, no, everybody agrees about how weighty it is, they're
just debating like what we make you do. But okay, but that
doesn't say why. That's just describing their two different approaches. Something symbolic
or the whole thing. Anyway, that's the debate. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: מעשה בהילני המלכה, Maaseh b'Helni HaMalka, a story with
Queen Helena, that she did seven years, she came to ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, בית הלל Beit Hillel says made her do another seven
years, then she became טמא tamei before the last moment and then
she had to do a whole another seven years again. איבעיא להו
ibaya lehu and then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, no, it was
only fourteen years. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: מה עשה,
Ma asa, איבעיא להו: ibaya lehu: בשנתמאית ואליבא דבית שמאי, bisnitmet v'aliba
d'Beit Shammai, when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that she only had
to do fourteen years, is he holding like בית שמאי Beit Shammai
and he agrees that she became טמאה, tme'ah, but what he just
says is she came to Israel, she had to do thirty days,
not seven years, because followed בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, and then she
became טמאה tme'ah and then she did another seven years? Is that
what he's saying? או דילמא בשלא נתמאית ואליבא דבית הלל, o dilma
b'shelo nitmet v'aliba d'Beit Hillel,
or is he agreeing that he followed בית הלל Beit Hillel and
it was seven plus seven, but she just doesn't agree that the
circumstances were that she became טמאה, tme'ah, she doesn't—that didn't happen. Okay,
so there's two ways to get fourteen years. Either she became טמאה
tme'ah but you don't hold like בית הלל, Beit Hillel, or you
hold like בית הלל Beit Hillel but she didn't become טמאה. tme'ah.
So the גמרא Gemara says תא שמע. ta shema. Come and hear:
עלתה לארץ והורוהו בית הלל שתהא נזירה עוד שבע שנים אחרות וכולי.
Atla l'Aretz v'horuhu Beit Hillel shetihei nezira od sheva shanim acherot v'chulu.
Okay, so they said seven more years and then she became טמאה.
tme'ah. And then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says his position: fourteen. ואי
סלקא דעתך בשנתמאית ואליבא דבית שמאי, V'is salka da'atach b'bisnitmet v'aliba d'Beit
Shammai,
if basically רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda held that she became טמאה tme'ah
and it was thirty days because—and yes she became טמאה, tme'ah, that
gets you to another seven years, that's fourteen, but it was only
thirty days additional because he held like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. אי
הכי, Ee hachi, רבי יהודה אומר היתה נזירה י"ד שנה, Rabbi Yehuda
omer hayta nezira yod-daled shana, why is he saying she was a
נזירה nezira for fourteen years? י"ד שנים ושלושים יום איבעיא ליה. Yod-daled
shanim u'shloshim yom ibaya lehu. He should have said fourteen years and
thirty days. Okay, so since he didn't say thirty days, sounds like
that he's only really—he's agreeing with בית הלל, Beit Hillel, he's only
just disagreeing that she did not become טמאה. tme'ah. תניא נמי הכי:
Tanya nami hachi: we also taught like this: ונתמאית, V'nitmet, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda אומר משום רבי אליעזר דאמר קרא: זאת תורת הנזיר. omer
mishum Rabbi Eliezer d'amar kra: zot torat hanazir. התורה אמרה כי נתמאית
ביום מלאות תן לה תורת נזיר. HaTorah amra ki nitmet b'yom milos
ten lah torat nazir. Now
what does this have to do with anything?
So, if you take a look... what...
okay. So now תוספות Tosafot says, one minute...
one minute... and תוספות Tosafot I think says takes out this whole
גרסא, girsa, one minute.
Yeah, so תוספות Tosafot I think takes out the next line, hold
on one second, although I'm not seeing it, hold on.
Yeah, because the next line really doesn't read so—doesn't read so well.
Like the next line—I mean all the next line has is that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, right, how does this show anything? רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says דאמר קרא: זאת תורת הנזיר. d'amar kra: zot
torat hanazir. התורה אמרה כי נתמאית ביום מלאות, HaTorah amra ki nitmet
b'yom milos, when she becomes טמאה tme'ah on the very last day,
תן לו תורת נזיר, ten lo torat nazir, you have to do
another thirty days. Now that actually seems to be... oh, wait, let
me think how this is, hold on one second.
Oh, right, right. If the incident happened on the last day, if
she became טמאה tme'ah and happened on the last day, then it
wouldn't have been...
then what? Then it wouldn't have been... then it wouldn't, no, but
it also wouldn't have been fourteen years, it would have only been
an additional thirty days.
It would be fourteen years plus thirty days.
Right, so it wouldn't have been twenty-one. Well, he—right,
but he already said it's not twenty-one. But he's saying—but the גמרא
Gemara is saying if it's the scenario that she did seven years
and then thirty days according to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, and then
she became טמאה tme'ah on day thirty, you wouldn't...
A, the first—I think like it's a different point. The first point
is then he shouldn't have said fourteen years, he should have said
fourteen years and thirty days. But B, I think the second point
is it wouldn't have been in another seven years because if she
became טמאה tme'ah on the last day following רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
it would only be another thirty days, right? So you wouldn't—so there's
two ways this doesn't work in the משנה.
mishna. Well, it could have been up to the second to last
day.
Well, it could have been up to the second... but the same
thing, it's two ways—what?
This could be proving that he holds that she just never got
טמאה.
tme'ah. I think you're exactly—it's saying if—if that's what it's saying: if
she got טמאה tme'ah and it's following בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, then
there's two ways it doesn't work in the משנה. mishna. Number one,
it would have been fourteen years and thirty days, not just fourteen
years. And B, it wouldn't have been fourteen years because if you
did seven years and thirty days and then became טמאה, tme'ah, right,
then it would have just been another thirty days because she's coming
טמאה tme'ah after, you know, any time from the last day on
would only be an additional thirty days. That seems to be the
point of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, let's now go to the next
משנה. mishna. מי שהיו שתי כיתי עדים... Mi shehayu shtei kitoi eidim...
מי שהיו שתי כיתי עדים מעידות אותו. Mi shehayu shtei kitei eidim
meidut oto.
So there are two sets of witnesses testifying about his status.
אלו מעידים שנזר שתיים ואלו מעידים שנזר חמש. Eilu meidim shenazar shtayim
ve'eilu meidim shenazar chamesh. These say, two say that he was made
a נזיר Nazir for two years and two say he made a
נזירות nezirot for five years. בית שמאי אומרים נחלקה העדות. Beit Shammai
omrim nechlaka ha'edut. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says, okay, they're contradicting, you
have no testimony, you're free to go, and there's no נזירות nezirot
at all. בית הלל אומרים יש בכלל חמש שתיים. Beit Hillel omrim
yesh bichlal chamesh shtayim.
No, but they say five, five also is, you know, a subset
of five is two, so at least the עדים eidim are all
agreeing that there was two years at least of נזירות, nezirot, two,
I mean two sets of נזירות. nezirot.
So now he has to be a נזיר Nazir for two rounds.
Now of course the question is what's he saying in all of
this. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot is bothered with the question, look, if
he's silent when the first כת kat of עדים eidim comes, why
don't we just say שתיקה כהודאה. shtika kehoda'ah. The first כת kat
of עדים eidim came, he was silent, what if they say five,
he basically admitted that it was five. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot has
two scenarios. One is that he's just denying everything the עדים eidim
say, or the other is is that the עדים eidim all came
at the same time, so his silence doesn't mean anything because they're
contradicting themselves, I don't have to say anything. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot
is bothered with the question about when why if he's being silent
why don't we interpret that as an admission. But I would also
ask the other question, let's say, you know, let's say they contradict
one another, you know, it's like why is it a question about
what the עדים eidim say, I mean isn't this sort of like
between him and God, you know. I mean, so the part of
the answer is like no, because part of נזירות nezirot is if
you violate it we're going to get lashes, you're going to get
lashes, right. There's also another question which comes up even about a
קרבן. korban. If witnesses say that I did a certain sin בשוגג,
beshogeg, okay, and I am denying it or not denying it or
whatever I'm doing, can the witnesses obligate me to bring a קרבן
korban or do we say look whether I'm חייב chayiv a קרבן
korban or not, that's between me and God, thank you very much,
I don't, you know, you guys keep out of it, right. So
that's an interesting question and that comes up. So there is an
opinion that when witnesses say I did a sin בשוגג, beshogeg, some
say well you've got to follow the witnesses and even if you're
denying you did the sin you've got to bring a קרבן korban
because that now בית דין Beit Din believes that you did that
sin. And there's another opinion that more or less says, I mean
I'm simplifying a lot, but that more or less says no, בית
דין Beit Din is not going to compel you to bring a
קרבן korban even with the witnesses. Now one way of explaining it
is because the witnesses can't exactly prove that you did it בשוגג,
beshogeg, maybe you did it במזיד, bemezid, how do they know the
exact circumstances. But another way of thinking about it is it's not
בית דין's Beit Din concern whether I bring a קרבן. korban. Okay,
so that's interesting in terms of a קרבן. korban. But here here
the point is that whether you're a נזיר Nazir or not has
a consequence not just for קרבן korban but for getting lashes, right,
because there's real violations that could be related to this. So what
is really quite fascinating is bringing עדים, eidim, I think I assume
that for you like for me it was a certain jarring, until
now it's all been about the person who accepted the נזירות nezirot
and their responsibility to God and maybe they seek to a rabbi
to figure out whether the נדר neder was binding or can you
do a התרה hatarah or whatever, right. But here you basically introduce
the sense of there's an external court system that needs to to
determine whether you're a נזיר Nazir and that's going to enforce some
element of it. So whether you're saying you are or you're not,
you know we're going to accept testimony and we're going to say
that that now we believe that you are and you have to
observe it even if you deny that you are.
Yes, what about intention as being required.
Oh, you mean let's say he says, yes I did say those
words I can't deny what the witnesses say, but I was just
fooling around, I wasn't doing it intentionally, right. So that's really a
good question because look, all along we've been dealing with the issue
about פיו ולבו שווים, piv velibo shavim, that it's not enough what
you say, it has to be what you think. And while on
the one hand we say that, on the other hand so much
of נדרים nedarim and נזיר Nazir seems like we don't ask the
guy what he was thinking, if he said the words and there's
not and the there's not a context that would make us redefine
it, we say he's a נזיר Nazir and it was never
fully explored let's say you have all the context and you have
the words and he says yes but I wasn't intending it, like
if he's believed or not, right. And so that wasn't never like
fully explicated. And it's an interesting question, I don't know the answer
to it which is
maybe the rules would be a little different for נזיר Nazir than
for a נדר neder because for a נזיר Nazir which is more
a concern of בית דין Beit Din maybe we don't trust you
as much in terms of what you were thinking, what you say
you were thinking, as opposed to a נדר neder which is like
less under the purview of בית דין. Beit Din. Now it's true
you could violate your נדר neder also and be deserving of lashes,
but somehow it seems that the person who's a נזיר Nazir his
status is more public, the opportunities for violation are greater, you know
are more ongoing, it seems like it's more of an area of
a בית דין Beit Din concern than a נדר. neder. But you
raise a very good question, right, what you're thinking is also relevant,
but it is very rare in the גמרא Gemara that the גמרא
Gemara says why don't why don't we ask him what he was
thinking, right, we didn't we haven't really seen that. All right, so
let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara. מתניתין דלא כי
האי תנא, Matnitin dela ki hai tanna, our משנה Mishnah is not
like the following תנא. tanna. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
braita, רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה אומר, Rabbi Yishmael
bno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka omer, here's again רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael son of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה, Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, ולא
נחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל על שתי כיתי עדים, velo nechelku Beit
Shammai veBeit Hillel al shtei kitei eidim, they did not disagree by
two sets of witnesses, אחת אומרת שתיים ואחת אומרת חמש, achat omeret
shtayim ve'achat omeret chamesh,
one says two and one says five. שיש בכלל חמש שתים, sheyesh
bichlal chamesh shtayim, that everybody would agree, look, they overlap for two,
so he's a נזיר nazir two, for two times. על מה נחלקו?
Al mah necheleku? What was the debate? על כת אחת. Al kat
achat. The debate is within one, one pair of witnesses themselves. אחד
אומר שתים ואחד אומר חמש. Echad omer shtayim v'echad omer chamesh. One
says two and one says five. One of the people, right? Of
the two witnesses, one, one witness says two and one says five.
שבית שמאי אומרים נחלקה העדות. SheBeit Shammai omrim necheleka ha'edut. So בית
שמאי Beit Shammai says you don't even have a pair of witnesses
here. ובית הלל אומרים יש בכלל חמש שתים. U'Beit Hillel omrim yesh
bichlal chamesh shtayim. No, they combine because the five includes two and
they're a good pair. So this way, I mean, I don't know
how you feel, but I feel that when it's two competing sets,
intuitively I agree with the idea that, okay, there's an overlap. Like
if one says five and one says two, even though they're saying
different things, can you really say that the one that says two
has been contradicted? Right? How much have they been contradicted? The other
said something that was even bigger. Okay, so it's not I wouldn't
call a five a contradiction to two. On the other hand, if
you have two people and one says five and one says two,
I might say the guy who says five hasn't contradicted two, but
to what degree are they testifying to the same thing that they
can be seen as joining together to create a unified testimony? Right?
That's a very different story. It's one thing to say you're not
really contradicting. It's another thing to say you're saying the same testimony
and that we combine the two. So it's interesting where the debate
was, whether בית הלל Beit Hillel would go so far as to
say it in the case of actually two people to combine their
testimony. Yes?
I maybe I maybe this is what you just said and I
did not follow. How is the גמרא Gemara reading the משנה Mishnah
to mean?
Not reading the משנה. Mishnah. It's a ברייתא braisa that disagrees with
what the debate of בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל Beit
Hillel was.
That's what I was gonna ask.
מתניתין דלא כהאי תנא. Matnitin d'lo k'hai tanna. Our משנה mishnah assumes
that their debate was about two sets of witnesses. רבי ישמעאל בנו
של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben
Broka says the debate was within a set of witnesses.
Right. It's a ברייתא braisa that has a different version of what
בית הלל Beit Hillel ובית שמאי u'Beit Shammai were debating. Okay, so
then it says like this. אמר רב, Amar Rav, says רב, Rav,
הכל מודים במונה. Hakol modim b'moneh. Everybody would agree if you were
counting, which means what? That the first set of witnesses said, or
maybe if it was two, you know, two people, if that was
the issue, but let's go with two sets of witnesses. The first
set of witnesses, this guy said I'm a נזיר nazir once and
twice. And the other person and the other set said, this guy
said I'm a נזיר nazir three times and four times and five
times. Okay, so there, there's like there's no contradiction because it's not
like they're saying a unit of five and a unit of two
where they're contradicting. If they're saying A and B and C and
D and E, it's more clear that the A and B from
both sets, you know, combine. Right? They're not a whole thing of
a different thing, right?
So so that seems to be the difference. Now the way that's
the way תוספות Tosafos says it, that the second set says he
said three and four and five. You could have said that the
first set said he said one and two and the second set
said he said one, two, three, four, five, right? So you actually
literally overlap in the one and the two. But either way, when
you're talking about them as discrete units, you can more see, oh,
for the first two discrete units they're saying the same thing rather
than when you talk about it as a totality of two and
a totality of five, you could say there's no overlap. Those are
conceptually different units, right? A small group and a big group. And
as opposed to here, you're looking at the individual numbers. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמרי רב חמא לרב חסדא מה קאמר?
Amrei Rav Chama l'Rav Chisda mah kama? What's he saying? אילימא אחד
אומר חמש ולא שתים, Ileima echad omer chamesh v'lo shtayim,
when he says מונה moneh means one guy says five and not
two. He said a five, he's not stopped at two. ואחד אומר
שתים ולא חמש, V'echad omer shtayim v'lo chamesh, he said two and
he didn't go up to five. הכא מכחשי אהדדי? Hacha machshi ahdadi?
So they're contradicting one another. Okay, and because they're explicitly excluding. אלא
אחד אומר אחת ושתים. Ella echad omer achas u'shtayim. Oh, I said
תוספות, Tosafos, it's גמרא Gemara just shows. Okay, anyway, one said, one
group said he said one and two. ואחד אומר שלש ארבע וחמש,
v'echad omer shalosh arba v'chamesh, three, four, five. And there maybe you
could say that everybody would agree that's not the same contradiction. Okay,
that they're not really contradicting because, again, you're looking at more as
individual units rather than as a totality.
Is these the numbers of years?
No, נזירות, nezirus, נזירות, nezirus, number of I think units of נזירות.
nezirus. Okay.
I'm a I'm gonna be a נזיר nazir one and two, one
time and actually two times. Right.
So the גמרא Gemara
says, הא למה לי השתא יש במחמירתא? Ha lamma li hashta yesh
b'machmirta? Amar רב Rav d'chasra meiya d'girsa d'Rav, קילתא לא אמר? kalsa
lo amar? So so why
so there's a hard גמרא Gemara to read, but anyway the way
תוספות Tosafos reads it, he takes out the word מחמירתא, machmirta, and
what he's saying is like this.
Why are you saying this? Meaning what's the logic here? Because השתא
יש במחמירתא אמר קילתא לא אמר? hashta yesh b'machmirta amar kalsa lo
amar? If he say or question mark, קילתא לא אמר? kalsa lo
amar? So if he were to say the weighty thing, three, four,
and five, so you know, how could he not be saying the
lighter thing, the one and the two? So by saying three, four,
and five, it's a hard גמרא Gemara to read, but anyway this
is the reading I'm going with. If he's saying the weighty thing,
how could he not be saying the lighter thing of the one
and the two?
אמר בין מרובא, Amar bin Maruva, so
מרובא... Maruva... All right, it was a little unclear how to exactly
parse that but הדרן עלך מי שאמר. Hadran Alakh Mi She'amar. So
that is the end of that and again what's more interesting to
me other than the question of is our contradiction 2 versus 5
or do we look at the overlap, you know and again the
difference between two sets where the question is how much are they
contradicted as opposed to one set which is how much are they
combining so that's a highest threshold, but is the idea that we're
introducing witnesses and we're introducing this so that it's a matter of
concern of the בית דין, beis din, you know and again maybe
even before the guy has transgressed, just the fact that this might
will be a matter of concern of us, we need to get
that information, we need to find that out right now.
What do you mean the highest threshold? What do you mean by
that?
That it's harder to say that things are saying are enough in
sync that they're combining to create a unified עדות eidus than to
saying that they don't contradict one another. Meaning that you say 5
doesn't contradict 2, you know is one thing, right, as opposed to
saying that 5 and 2 are basically can combine to create one
עדות eidus when it's two people, that's just that's harder to say.
Okay, so now we begin the next פרק. perek. Okay, yes, רש״י
Rashi says it's years.
Oh,
he says it's years?
Because well that's
because what that was the context before was a context of years.
תוספות Tosafos doesn't say that. תוספות Tosafos שתי נזירות. shtei neziros. He
talks about we've just we've just
sort of rewritten the entire thing. Well,
okay.
All right. Next, go thank you. Let's go to the next פרק.
perek. מי שאמר הריני נזיר ושמע חברו ואמר ואני. Mi she'amar ha-reini
Nazir v'shama chaveiro v'amar v'ani. This is something that we have seen
in similar forms elsewhere. Somebody said הריני נזיר ha-reini Nazir and his
friend said ואני v'ani and me too
and the next guy said ואני v'ani and me too. כולם נזירים,
Kulam nezirim, they're all נזירים. nezirim. Okay, because each one piggybacks on
the next guy. Now the question is is when guy number three
says ואני v'ani and me, is he saying is his and me
going on guy number one or is and me going on guy
number two? So we'll see that in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. הותר
הראשון Hutar ha-rishon and it's actually pretty clear I think from the
משנה Mishnah which one it means because let's look at this הלכה.
halakha. הותר הראשון, Hutar ha-rishon,
if the first one gets his נזירות nezirus undone, he goes to
a חכם chakham and he gets a היתר hetter retroactively, it means
he was never a נזיר, nazir, הותרו כולם, hutru kulam, then they're
all undone because they basically
exactly because basically here's the question about how to look at it,
right? Do you say that when somebody says ואני, v'ani, it's sort
of like a יד, yad, right? And if it's a יד yad
in the context where you said I'm a נזיר nazir and I
said me too, those words me too just mean I'm a נזיר.
nazir. If that's all it meant then it wouldn't matter whether your
status wound up taking effect for you or not, it got undone
because that's you know in this context my words me too just
means I'm a נזיר. nazir. But it seems like from this משנה
Mishnah it's more than that. Me too basically means my נזירות nezirus
is just like your נזירות nezirus and somehow I am transferring your
status to me. Okay, whatever status applies to you applies to me.
So that's like התפסה, hatfasa, right? You know התפסה hatfasa is like
זה כזה, ze k'ze, right? You transfer the status of a certain
thing that's אסור בנדר asur b'neder or קרבן korban to another object.
So you became a נזיר, nazir, so that also whatever your status
is I'm applying it to me. So if your status went away
I didn't apply anything to me. Okay, so that's הותר הראשון הותרו
כולם. hutar ha-rishon hutru kulam. הותר האחרון, Hutar ha-akharon, if guy number
three got undone, האחרון מותר, ha-akharon muttar, so fine that because he
was the bottom of the chain, you cut him off, but the
top of the chain is still there. האחרון מותר וכולם אסורים, Ha-akharon
muttar v'kulam asurim, everybody else remains forbidden. Now the interesting thing is
going to be what do you think according to this משנה Mishnah
if guy number two gets it undone?
Right, presumably guy number three would be undone and guy number one
would be still a נזיר. nazir. That's what the ברייתא's Baraita going
to say, but interestingly the גמרא Gemara is not going to be
so clear about that because the גמרא Gemara wants to wonder you
know whether
when guy number three said me too, is his me too going
on guy two or is me too going on guy one, right?
So that's going to be the question in the גמרא. Gemara. But
the conclusion is going to be not to ruin the surprise and
I think it's pretty implicit in the משנה Mishnah and we've seen
we've seen this before is that no, the me too of guy
three is going on guy two. So if guy two gets undone,
it impacts guy three.
I know spoiler alert, okay everybody close your eyes. Okay, so now
okay
now אמר הריני נזיר amar ha-reini Nazir guy says I'm a נזיר
nazir ושמע חברו ואמר פי כפי, v'shama chaveiro v'amar pi k'fiv, my
mouth like his mouth ושערי כשערו v'sa'ari k'sa'aro and my hair like
his hair, הרי זה נזיר, harei ze Nazir, he's a נזיר. nazir.
Now that's interesting because פי כפי, pi k'fiv, I mean what does
that mean like I won't drink wine like he won't drink wine
or does פי כפי pi k'fiv mean just like he took the
vow I'm taking the vow, right? And then these two phrases are
different because then the פי כפי pi k'fiv focuses on the act
of taking the vow and שערי כשערו sa'ari k'sa'aro focuses on the
state of being a נזיר. nazir. So anyway the גמרא Gemara will
unpack that. But anyway that makes him a נזיר nazir as well.
הריני נזיר Ha-reini Nazir ושמעה אשתו ואמרה ואני, v'sham'ah ishto v'amra v'ani,
I'm a נזיר nazir and his wife heard and she said and
me too. מיפר את שלה, Mefer es shelah, so he can annul
the wife's part because that's his prerogative as a husband ושלו קיים
v'shelo kayam and it doesn't affect his part, his part is still
standing. Now let's say it was another case. She said הריני נזירה,
Ha-reini nezira, I'm a נזירה nezira ושמע בעלה ואמר ואני v'shama ba'ala
v'amar v'ani and he said and me. אינו יכול להפר, Eino yachol
lehafer,
he cannot annul it. Now why can he not annul it?
He can't annul his own.
Okay, so one reason could be that the annulling of his wife's
will have the effect of annulling his own. Now why can't he
annul his own? Right? Okay, indirectly I managed to annul my own.
I can go to a חכם Chacham and get it done-done. I
annulled my wife and that affected mine as being undone. You know,
why can't I undo it? So the גמרא... Gemara... so that could
be because of a פסוק pasuk that says לא יחל דברו. Lo
yachel devaro. He... his words cannot be violated or cannot be annulled,
cannot be, cannot be sort of right, you know, avoided. And the
גמרא Gemara says הוא אינו מיחל דברו אבל אחרים מתירין ומוחלין לו.
Hu eino mechal devaro aval acheirim matirin u'mochlin lo. That's the basis
for how a חכם Chacham can be מתיר. matir. You can't do
it for yourself, but you can go to a חכם Chacham and
a חכם Chacham can undo it. So one way of reading that
is, ah, but the point is you can't do it yourself. So
even if you somehow find a legal means to do it to
yourself by this way of annulling your wife's and therefore it annuls
your own, you're not allowed to do that. That's one way of
reading it. The other way is, I mean we'll see about this
in the גמרא. Gemara. I'm just giving you another spoiler alert for
the גמרא. Gemara. The other way of doing this is saying this
is no, it has nothing to do with that. It's that as
soon as his wife said הריני נזירה Hareini nezira and he said
ואני, V'ani, that's an act of קיום, kiyum, right? Oh, so you
like the fact that she's a נזיר, nazir, so now you're the
קיום. kiyum. You can't do a הפרה. hafara. Okay. So he couldn't
do it for the wife either? Exactly. Ah, right, because that's what
it says. It says אינו יכול להפר, Eino yachol lehafer,
right. It's not that he can't do it for himself. Meaning either
way you do it, you read what the reason is, he can't
do it for his wife. Either because doing it for his wife
will undo it for him or because he was already מקיים mekayeim
for his wife.
But then you couldn't say that he could... he could be מיפר
meifer hers but it wouldn't apply to him?
I mean, I mean you could say לא יחל דברו Lo yachel
devaro means it won't be effective, not that he's not allowed. I
mean, but yes, but we're not saying that. We're reading the משנה
Mishna that he's not allowed to be מיפר meifer his wife. So
the way one would be saying he's not allowed to be מיפר
meifer his wife because it would violate the principle of לא יחל
דברו. Lo yachel devaro. So therefore it doesn't even... he can't even
do the whole thing. Okay, and presumably if he did it, it
wouldn't be effective. But the easier read is just that he can't
do it because he was already מקיים. mekayeim.
No, because when he said ואני v'ani
he was being מקיים mekayeim his wife.
Exactly, and he's then
becoming the קיום.
kiyum. Then can he go seek a התרה hatara for himself? What?
Can he go
to a חכם Chacham for a התרה? hatara? Yeah, and can he
do a התרה hatara for a קיום? kiyum? Because we had that
discussion before. Can you be מתיר matir the קיום? kiyum? If you
do מתיר, matir, if you do a התרה, hatara, right, for your
own ואני, v'ani, and then it undoes his own נזירות nezirot and
it undoes his own קיום, kiyum, and then he could also be
מיפר meifer his wife's though? Maybe that he could do, right.
Okay, now
הריני נזיר ואת. Hareini nazir v'at. He says I'm a נזיר nazir
and how about you? Okay, or he says and you, but even
if he meant and you, he doesn't have the right to say
and you, so we don't... that itself doesn't do anything, you can't
make your wife into a נזיר, nazir, okay? ואמרה V'amra
and she says אמן, Amen, yes, that's a good idea, I'll be
a נזיר nazir with you. Okay, so that's what happens. מיפר שלה,
Meifer shelah, he can annul hers, ושלך קיים v'shelo kayam but you
know his remains because again, hers... hers came, you know, derived from
his. Now if she says הריני נזירה ואתה Hareini nezira v'ata and
I'm a נזירה nezira and you too buddy or and you? question
mark. Either way it requires him to say אמן. Amen. ואמר אמן
V'amar Amen and he says אמן. Amen. אינו יכול להפר Eino yachol
lehafer then he can't, for the same reason. He's dependent on her
and his אמן Amen is a type of a קיום. kiyum. So
therefore he cannot. All right, very nice. Let's take a look at
the
גמרא. Gemara. יתיב ריש לקיש קמיה דרבי יהודה נשיאה. Yativ Reish Lakish
kaman d'Rabbi Yehuda Nesia. Reish Lakish was sitting in front of Rabbi
Yehuda Nesia, the grandson of Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi. ויתיב וקאמר V'yativ v'ka'amar and sitting and saying והוא שהתפיסו כולן
בתוך כדי דיבור. v'hu she-hitpisu kulan betoch kedei dibbur. So Reish Lakish
is going to assume number one
that when two, three, and four and five and however many people
say ואני, ואני, ואני, v'ani, v'ani, v'ani,
they're all saying it back on number one, right? It's not that
two goes on one and three goes on two that we've just
discussed. He's going to assume they all go on number one. And
he's going to say that the ואני v'ani only works in a
context of תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, which is within the
amount of time that it takes to say two or three words,
we'll see, like שלום עליך רבי Shalom alecha rebbi or שלום עליך...
Shalom alecha... okay, we'll take a look at that. Now, which is
interesting, right? Because you would say like when we said for example
היה נזיר עובר לפניו ואמר ואני, Haya nazir over lefanav v'amar v'ani,
right? Classic example where it works with a יד. yad. Do we
say that only works if you said it within תוך כדי דיבור
toch kedei dibbur of the time that he passed? We've never said
that, right? That created a certain context. Now, exactly how long does
that context consider to still be around is an interesting question. But
you know, we have an idea for example of like עסוקין באותו
עניין. asukin be'oto inyan. You know, somehow you're still within the context
of the conversation and that gives frames what the words are that
you're saying. It puts them in that context. Okay, here though it
seems again like we're saying before, it's not just because you said
הריני נזיר Hareini nazir now that creates a context for what ואני
v'ani means. No, what I actually am doing is I am extending
your status to me. Okay, and and the fact that I said
it like again, you weren't just a נזיר nazir walking in front
of me and I said ואני. v'ani. That would be like one
case. Okay, that's actually by the way... thinking about this now. Let's
say you had a נזיר nazir passing in front of you and
you said ואני. va'ani. You didn't hear him take the נזירות. nezirot.
You just saw the guy with the long hair and you said
ואני. va'ani. And then that נזיר nazir got a היתר heter for
his נדר neder for his נזירות. nezirot. Would yours be undone? Would
that ואני va'ani be a יד? yad? And no, that's just a
context. But I just סתם stam said I'm a נזיר. nazir. Or
did I say I'm transferring his status to me, right? I don't
know. But here, what you're doing is you're actually piggybacking on the
words themselves, right? It's not just creating that context that now makes
your word into a יד. yad. You're piggybacking on the words themselves.
So to have you to piggyback and have those words essentially be
like your words, right, it has to be תוך כדי דיבור. toch
k'dei dibbur. That's right, but my point is right that that's a
חידוש. chiddush. I'm not sure I would have thought of that or
assumed that, yeah, because I would assume here's a context, he said,
דיבור dibbur is when I say something, I have תוך כדי דיבור
toch k'dei dibbur to retract it, to edit it, go back, right,
but when you're saying it, I understand, but that's only because we're
assuming that your speech act is piggybacking on mine. I get it.
Okay, but not that you're just it's not just my act is
creating a context for what your thing means, you're actually extending my
speech act essentially to you. That's what we're saying.
And that's what happens when you make a mistake
in תפילה tefillah תוך כדי דיבור? toch k'dei dibbur? I understand, but
here's a חידוש, chiddush, here's a I get it, I'm just saying
I'm pointing that out, that there's a second person involved. You could
have explained it differently, you could have explained that the first guy
just created the framework, the context, but we're not saying that. The
same way we're saying that when one of the guys gets undone,
it has this ripple effect, we're not just saying that you created
a scene and a context, the people that come afterwards are actually
participating in that same act. That's exactly what we're saying. And they
do תוך כדי
דיבור
toch
k'dei
dibbur and הייא עבר לפנינו haya over lefanenu because הייא עבר לפנינו
haya over lefanenu is an independent
phenomenon that's occurring and when that's over it's over. But speech, as
soon as you finish, as soon as the words are out of
your mouth, it's done.
Right, so we're
investigating, you know, how long does that context extend, right, which you
don't have to apply to הייא עבר לפנינו haya over lefanenu because
as soon as he turns the corner, he's gone.
No, I understand that, but look, let me give you an example.
I normally if I give a ring to a woman and say
הרי את מקודשת לי, harei at mekudeshet li, right, I need to
say something to give so that it's an act of קידושין. kiddushin.
But let's say we're sitting around and we're talking about getting married,
okay, and I never said the words הרי את מקודשת לי harei
at mekudeshet li and we're sitting there with the in-laws and we're
planning the wedding and whatever and then I just get up in
the middle of that and I give a ring without saying anything.
You know, so we would say עסוקים באותו עניין asukin be'oto inyan
and that's implicit from the context that it's קידושין kiddushin and she's
married, right? It would not only be when it was within תוך
כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur of the last person who just got
finished speaking, right, because it's not about that's just creating a context
for giving meaning to my action. So that's my point here, right?
And again, you could say this is all obvious, but I'm just
supporting, fine, it's obvious, I'm just pointing it out that what here
is not that the act of talking gives context to my words
ואני. va'ani. The point is my ואני va'ani is
piggybacking and participating in your act of speech, okay, and therefore it
has to be תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur with your act
of speech. Fine, it's obvious, but that's what we're saying. Okay, and
that's why, right, and the same reason why when it gets undone
for you, it gets undone for me, because I actually am now
extending your act of speech to me and that's what requires תוך
כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur. So that's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says. So let's take a look. והוא שהתפיסו כולם בתוך כדי דיבור.
vehu she'hitpisu kulam be'toch k'dei dibbur. וכמה תוך כדי דיבור? vekama toch
k'dei dibbur? How much is it? כדי שאילת שלום, kedei she'ilat shalom,
like asking after the well-being of somebody, you know, שלום עליך. shalom
alecha.
וכמה כדי שאילת שלום? vekama kedei she'ilat shalom? How much is that?
כדי שיאמר שלום תלמיד לרב. kedei sheyomar shalom talmid l'rav. So it's
now this is the question, is it רב לתלמיד rav l'talmid and
it's just שלום עליך, shalom alecha, or is it תלמיד לרב talmid
l'rav which is שלום עליך רבי shalom alecha rebbi or something so
maybe it might be שלום עליך רבי ומורי shalom alecha rebbi u'mori
depending on whether it's a you know רב מובהק rav muvhak or
whatever. Anyway, so many hours longer. So yes, exactly. Two words or
three words? Everything matters. Two words or three words. So אמר ליה,
amar lei, so what only three words? So he said back to
him, אמר ליה, amar lei, תוב, tov, sit down or whatever, go
back, לא שבקת רבך לתלמידה, lo shavkat ravcha l'talmida, you're not giving
any space for the student. Like what? So the way תוספות Tosafot
explains that is it means, so I don't get it, here's somebody's
passing in front of me, somebody says הריני נזיר hareini nazir and
I want to say ואני, va'ani, but at that moment my רבי
rebbi pops into the room so I have to go ahead and
say שלום עליך רבי shalom alecha rebbi and then I wouldn't by
the time I say ואני, va'ani, I don't have a chance to
say ואני va'ani because it's too late.
So I don't know, anyway, somehow it was a way of saying
like no, no, no, that's that's not giving enough time. No, no,
it's not only three words. Now why not? Like doesn't he doesn't
he agree with the idea of תוך כדי דיבור? toch k'dei dibbur?
This is how it's classically defined, two words, three words, and so
on. So it could be like I've been trying to put out
there that it's not obvious that it should be based on the
תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur model. Maybe saying you've got a
little more time, this guy says it, you say ואני, va'ani, who
says
you need to
immediately following תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur. So within, so, and
that you can by the way, if that sounds weird, here let
me explain why it makes sense. Because this is a תוך כדי
דיבור toch k'dei dibbur of a different person, a different person is
participating in it. So if I said, let's say another example ברוך
אתה ה' אלקינו מלך העולם שהכל נהיה בדברו, Baruch ata Hashem Elokeinu
melech ha'olam shehakol nihiya bidvaro, בורא פרי הגפן, borei pri hagafen, okay,
and I did a תוך כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur, right? So
I fixed it in time. So my תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei
dibbur is the time that my speech act is considered to still
be going, that it can after, like, the sort of the shadow
cast or whatever, you know, of my speech act, that it's still
somehow potentially going and it can still be edited. So by the
time the תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur is over, that's when
my speech act is over. Then if you jump in right there,
you've jumped in right after my speech act finished. You don't have
to be in my speech act, you just have to be juxtaposed
to my speech act. So that seems to be why here he's
saying it can be immediately following תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur.
For you to correct what you said, you have to be within
תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur. For me to piggyback on what
you said, I can go right after your תוך כדי דיבור. toch
k'dei dibbur. So that's an interesting debate. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami
hachi, we taught similarly like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that it's within
תוך כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur, not after תוך כדי דיבור. toch
k'dei dibbur. מי שאמר הריני נזיר ושמע חבירו ושהה כדי דיבור ואמר
ואני, Mi she'amar hareni nazir v'shama chaveiro v'shaha k'dei dibbur v'amar va'ani,
הוא אסור וחבירו מותר. hu assur v'chaveiro mutar.
So if the guy waited כדי דיבור k'dei dibbur and then said
ואני, va'ani, he is not a נזיר, nazir, only the first person
is. וכמה כדי דיבור? V'chama k'dei dibbur? And how much is it?
כדי שאילת תלמיד לרב. K'dei she'eilas talmid l'rav. Okay, so that's what
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said. So it's your classic תוך כדי דיבור,
toch k'dei dibbur, even the other even though the other approach I
think was like interesting to explore how it might be a little
bit of a variation of it. לימא מסייע ליה, Leima mesayei lei,
let's try to support this. מי שאמר הריני נזיר ושמע חבירו ואמר
ואני ואני ותו לא. Mi she'amar hareni nazir v'shama chaveiro v'amar va'ani
va'ani v'su lo.
So in our משנה Mishna it just has guys two and three,
right? So why does it only have guys two and three if
you actually can go up to you know three words, you can
have or four words, you can have guys three and four, right?
You got it? If תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur is you
know more than three words, you could have even four guys within
תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur of guy number one. We're assuming
it's all they're all piggybacking on guy number one. Okay.
Can I ask a question? Yeah. But is it תוך כדי דיבור
toch k'dei dibbur in other words, the original guy?
That's what I'm saying.
That's in other words.
That's what I keep on saying.
That's what I keep on saying, that the assumption at this stage,
we're going to change it, but the assumption at this stage is
all the guys that come later are all piggybacking on guy number
one's statement. And they have to be within תוך כדי דיבור toch
k'dei dibbur of guy number one. Yes. That's the assumption the גמרא
Gemara is making. Okay. We're right, we're going to revise that in
a minute, but that's the assumption.
If you calculate it out, if number three was dropped out, then
four and five dropped out, that wouldn't apply now if four and
five.
Correct. Correct. So the משנה Mishna was never clear what happens if
a middle guy gets a היתר. heter. We spoke about the first
guy and the last guy. We assumed, and the גמרא Gemara is
going to conclude this way, that was my spoiler, that if the
middle guy got a היתר, heter, it would affect everybody below him.
But you don't have to read the משנה Mishna that way. You
could read it everybody who comes later is connecting back to number
one. And that any middle guy affects nobody. The only person who
affects people is number one. Okay, so that's the assumption we're making
now. ושמע חבירו ואמר ואני ואני ותו לא, v'shama chaveiro v'amar va'ani
va'ani v'su lo,
and no more. So you see that it sounds like two people
and not like if you say תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur
is like you know four, it goes after תוך כדי דיבור, toch
k'dei dibbur, you get up to four people. Why is the משנה
Mishna ending there? Of course, you could say that even if תוך
כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur means שלום עליך רבי, Shalom alecha rabbi,
it should have said three people. Why does it only say two
people? But okay, that's the גמרא's Gemara's question. Why only two? So
does that prove that we're talking with a very small תוך כדי
דיבור? toch k'dei dibbur? גמרא Gemara says no, תנא כי רוכלא ליחשוב
וליזיל? tana k'ruchla lachshov v'leizil? Is the is the תנא Tanna going
to like a merchant to go ahead and like list all of
his wares? You know, I mean, okay, you know what I'm saying?
ואני ואני ואני ואני, Va'ani va'ani va'ani va'ani, you get the point.
Okay. Okay. Now, so the
גמרא Gemara says וליתני חד, v'lisnei chad, okay, so if you say
he doesn't have to go on and on, why does he talk
about guys two and three? Just talk about guy number two. וליתני
הנך V'lisnei hanoch and you know and like we'll figure out the
rest. הכי נמי, Hachi nami, yeah you're right, it could have just
said number two. So why did it say two and three? ומשום
דקתני סיפא הותר ראשון הותרו כולן הותר אחרון אחרון מותר וכולן אסורין.
Umishum d'katani seifa hutar rishon hutru kullan hutar acharon acharon mutar v'kullan
assurin. Since in
one of them it talks about what happens if it's the first
guy, that affects multiple people, guys two and three. And if it's
the last guy, it doesn't affect anybody. מכלל דאיכא מיצעא, Michlal d'ika
meitza'a,
so we want to be talking about a middle guy. ומשום הכי
קתני ואני ואני, Umishum hachi katani va'ani va'ani, and it says and
I and I. So we want to take the more interesting case
when you deal with three, right, than when you deal with two,
right? So we want to deal with three, but we're not listing
all of the number of people that are possible to piggyback. Is
it three people that can piggyback? Is it four people? We're not
discussing that. You can't infer from the fact that we gave a
scenario of three people what's the extent of how many people can
piggyback. Okay, איבעיא להו. ibaya lehu. Now we're going to, now that
we've raised that question, which is, is תוך כדי דיבור tokh kedei
dibbur three words or four words, or whatever, is it right after
תוך כדי דיבור tokh kedei dibbur so it gives you an a
little extra time. We're going to raise the following question, which is,
do they all piggyback on one or do they piggyback on the
guy right at right before them? איבעיא להו. ibaya lehu. חד בתר
חד מתפיס chad batar chad matpis או דילמא בקמא מתפיס. o dilma
bekamma matpis. Is each one being מתפיס matpis like grabbing onto, transferring
the status of the guy right right before him? Or are they
all going back to guy number one? Okay, now. מאי נפקא מינה,
mai nafka mina, what's a נפקא מינה? nafka mina? So the obvious
נפקא מינה nafka mina is obvious, it's what we've just been talking
about. לרפוסי ומיזל, lerapusei u-meizal, whether you can go on ad infinitum.
אי אמרת חד בתר חד מתפיס, ei amrat chad batar chad matpis,
each body is person is piggybacking on the guy right before him.
חזי ואזיל לעולם, chazi ve-azeil le-olam, you can go on forever. ואי
אמרת בקמא מתפיס, ve-ei amrat bekamma matpis, if everybody's just piggybacking on
guy number one, טפי מכדי דיבור לא מתפיסינן, tefei mikdei dibbur lo
matpisinan, then the כדי דיבור kedei dibbur all goes by the כדי
דיבור kedei dibbur of guy number one. Right? I
mean, כדי דיבור's kedei dibbur still relevant if you go by the
guy before you, that you have to be within כדי דיבור kedei
dibbur of the guy before you. But if you're always going to
guy number one, then you only have the space of like three
or four people that can be part of this little process. Okay.
What?
And then they don't know who's first, second, or third. More time?
If they just sign simultaneously.
Right, that's true, that's true. You get 10 people saying ואני va-ani
at once. Right. Exactly. So it's not relevant. But if they're all
piggybacking on guy number one, it doesn't matter who's second, third, right?
Because guy number one is the only person whose status affects everybody
else. Okay.
But if they all said it at once, then there'd be no
middle person.
That would be true, right, correct. Okay, so מאי, mai, what's the
halacha, what's the story? תא שמע. ta shema. הריני נזיר ושמע חבירו
ואמר ואני ואני וסולא מידי. hareini nazir ve-shama chaveiro ve-amar va-ani va-ani
ve-sula midi. It only goes up to two and three, so it
seems like it's telling you there's a limited way degree to which
you can keep on going down this chain. שמע מינה בקמא הוא
דמתפיס. shema mina bekamma hu de-matpis. You see it's they're all going
just on guy number one, that's a very limited number of people
that can piggyback. דאי סלקא דעתך חד בתר חד מתפיס, de-ei salka
de-atakh chad batar chad matpis, if you can everybody's going to the
guy before him, ליתני טובא ואני. litnei tuva va-ani. Say, say a
lot, ואני ואני ואני ואני ואני, va-ani va-ani va-ani va-ani va-ani, show
me that it can be a very long chain.
Exactly. So that's what the Gemara's going to say. What? תנא כי
רוכלא ליחשוב וליזיל? tanna ki rokhla leichshev u-leizeil?
Like you want it like a like a spice merchant to go
and to be shouting off its wares? Like give me a break,
it doesn't, you know, it doesn't have to say everyone. Okay. וליתני
חד וליתנו כולהו. ve-litni chad ve-litnu kulhu.
So fine. If that's true, why give us even two people? Just
give us one person who said ואני. va-ani. So, like we said
before, because two is much more interesting, two allows for a middle
person. איידי דקתני הותר הראשון הותרו כולן הותר אחרון אחרון מותר וכולן
אסורין. eidi de-katani hutar ha-rishon hutru kulan hutar acharon acharon mutar ve-kulan
asurin. So you do the last guy affects everybody, the first guy
affects everybody, the last guy it only affects himself. So therefore מכלל
דאיכא אמצעי. miklal de-ika emtzai. So we want to be talking about
a case where there's a first, a last, and a middle. משום
הכי קתני ואני ואני. mishum hachi katani va-ani va-ani. But you cannot
infer from the fact that it mentioned two guys that it's a
short list and not a potentially long list either. Okay. תא שמע.
ta shema. הותר הראשון הותרו כולן. hutar ha-rishon hutru kulan. Now we
get to a real נפקא מינה nafka mina besides the תוך כדי
דיבור, tokh kedei dibbur, besides the number of guys. הותר הראשון הותרו
כולן. hutar ha-rishon hutru kulan. If the first guy is released, they're
all released. ראשון הוא דשרו. rishon hu de-sharu. So here it's inferring
only if the first guy is released does it affect anybody. הא
אמצעי, ha emtzai, if it was a middle guy who was released,
לא, lo, it wouldn't affect anyone. Okay. שמע מינה בקמא מתפיסינן. shema
mina bekamma matpisinan. You see it's only the first guy's status who
matters because the Mishna only talks that if the first guy is
released, it has an impact. It doesn't talk about a middle guy
being released and what the impact would be. So the Gemara says,
no. אימא לך לעולם חד בתר חד
מתפיס. eima lakh le-olam chad batar chad matpis. Everybody's piggybacking on the
guy before him. ואיידי דבעי למיתני הותרו כולן. ve-eidi de-baei le-mitni hutru
kulan.
But it wanted to give an example where everybody gets released. So
therefore it wanted to talk about the first guy. דאי תנא אמצעי,
de-ei tana emtzai, if it talked about a middle guy, איכא ראשון
דלא משתרי. ika rishon de-la mishtarei. It wouldn't have been able to
say everybody's permissible, it would have only been able to say the
people following him is permissible. משום הכי תני ראשון. mishum hachi tani
rishon.
So we focus on the first guy, but it's not that the
first guy is the only person whose status matters, but he's an
interesting example because when you undo him, everybody gets undone. But maybe
a middle guy also would affect the people below him. All right,
let's try back to the Mishna. תא שמע. ta shema. הותר האחרון
האחרון מותר וכולן אסורין. hutar ha-acharon ha-acharon mutar ve-kulan asurin.
The last guy is released,
the last guy is permissible, and everybody before him is forbidden. So,
אחרון דלא איכא אחריני בתריה. acharon de-lo ika achrinei batrei. Because the
last guy is undone, he doesn't affect anybody because nobody follows him.
So the here the implication is in the opposite direction. The only
person who doesn't affect anybody is the last guy. אבל אמצעי, aval
emtzai, the implication is a middle guy, דאיכא אחריני בתריה, de-ika achrinei
batrei, that there's somebody who follows him, משתרי, mishtarei, he would affect
people below him. שמע מינה חד בתר חד מתפיס. shema mina chad
batar chad matpis. So that sounds like you're piggybacking on the guy
before you. לעולם אימא לך le-olam eima lakh no, בקמא מתפיסינן. bekamma
matpisinan. Everybody goes to guy number one. So if that's true, if
everybody goes to guy number one, here there's a real question: Tell
me a more interesting halacha. Tell me not only if guy three
gets released doesn't he affect anybody, even if guy two gets released
he doesn't affect anybody. Right? That's a more interesting halacha. Right? That's
a real good question. So if it's really true that they're all
piggybacking on guy number one, tell me even if guy number two
is released nobody's affected. Affected. So the גמרא Gemara says, ומאי אחרון
אלא, umai achron ella, okay, that's what it means. When it says
if the last guy is released nobody is affected, דקתני, dekatani, אחרון
achron doesn't mean the last guy. It means the middle guy. ואיידי
דתני רישא תני אחרון. ve-aydi de-tani reisha tani achron. So אחרון achron
really means anybody other than the first guy. Okay, so this is,
I mean, it's a hard read of the משנה, Mishna, because he
has a really good question. If there are three guys and you're
telling me if guy number two is released nobody's affected, so why
does the משנה Mishna say if the last guy is released nobody
is affected? Tell me if the middle guy is released nobody is
affected, that's a bigger חידוש. chiddush. So the גמרא Gemara says, well,
that's what it means. It means if anybody other than the first
guy. אחרון achron doesn't mean אחרון, achron, it means anybody other than
the first, which is a pretty hard read of the משנה, Mishna,
but that's what it says.
Anybody other than the first, everyone individually.
Right, that's how you would sustain that read. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara
is going to finally say what we sort of I think always
knew was coming. תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, דתניא בהדיא,
detanya behedya, we taught in an explicit ברייתא: Beraita: הותר הראשון הותרו
כולן, hutar harishon hutru kullan, if the first guy's released they're all
released; הותר האחרון האחרון מותר וכולן אסורין, hutar ha-achron ha-achron mutar ve-kullan
asurin, the last guy's released, only he is released, nobody else; הותר
האמצעי הימנו ולמטה מותר הימנו ולמעלה אסור, hutar ha-emtzai heimenu u-lemata mutar
heimenu u-lemala assur, if the middle guy is released,
from him downward is permissible,
from him upward is forbidden; שמע מינה חב בה דחבריה מצי, shema
mina chav beh de-chavreih matzi, so you see we're saying each one
piggybacks on the guy right before him; שמע מינה, shema mina, that
is a good proof. Okay, now again what one always wonders about
this is sort of it a little bit goes back to the
question that David was asking is, you know, about like making objective
statements and we don't ask what the guy is thinking. You know,
this might be as a default that's how we would interpret it,
but you could imagine circumstances in which it would make it very
clear that that wouldn't be the case, right? You said ואני, ve-ani,
I wasn't in earshot of you, or this side I don't hear
so well out of this ear, but I heard the first guy
and I said ואני, ve-ani, you know, or I was looking at
the first guy and I said ואני, ve-ani, I wasn't looking at
you, you know. So there's ways in which one wonders, is this
objectively how we're always going to define it halachically, or is this
in absence of there being a context that makes it clearer that
something else was going on? You know, also not really clear in
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, we'll end with this. כתיבה וחתימה טובה. ketiva
ve-chatima tova.